Guide to the Charles T. Davis Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Research and Teaching Files, 1936-1980; Series II; 14.87; (18 boxes)
  - A Study in the Unity of Moby Dick; Senior Honors Thesis by Ree Lazarus (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous writings, printed material (Box 12)
  - Tiegs, Ernest W. (Box 12)
  - Novelette by R. Lynn (Box 12)
  - Students: creative work
  - Printed material (Box 12)
  - Whitman chapter (Box 12)
  - The Child of Nature and Faust; Thesis by Karen L. Smith (Box 12)
  - Educational materials (Box 12)
  - Professional file (Box 12)
  - Faculty / Staff Directory, 1969-1970 (Box 13)
  - Notes (Box 13)
  - Professional correspondence (Box 13)
  - Davis's dissertation (Box 13)
  - E. A. Robinson - Remhart (Box 13)
  - Invoices (Box 13)
  - Davis's dissertation (Box 14)
  - Notes for dissertation, 10 (Box 14)
  - Whitman and Dickinson (Box 15)
  - Whitman recital and WNYC Book Festival, 1955 (Box 15)
  - Whitman lectures in India (Box 15)
  - Whitman papers from Simla conference (Box 15)
  - Walt Whitman and the Problem of an American Tradition (Box 15)
  - Emily Dickinson (Box 15)
  - Henry James (Box 15)
  - Mark Twain (Box 15)
  - Sidney Lanier (Box 15)
  - William Dean Howells (Box 15)
  - Cable, Harris and the New South (Box 15)
  - Introduction: American Poetry of the Mid & Late 19th Century (Box 15)
  - Edith Wharton (Box 15)
  - Norris and S. Crane (Box 15)
  - Robinson: Chapters 1 & 2, "The Roots" & "The Individual Talent" (Box 15)
  - Robinson: notes, variants, Poe poem, letters (Box 15)
  - Reviews (Box 15)
  - Robinson drafts (Box 15)
  - Robinson notes (Box 15)
  - Robinson and Dramatic Strategy (Box 15)
  - E. A. Robinson: Paradox and Beyond (Box 15)
  - Robinson's dramas (Box 15)
  - Robinson, E. A.: notes from letters (Box 15)
  - Lecture notes: E. A. Robinson (Box 15)
  - Robinson and W. James, H. James, Myers, Spengler and others (Box 15)
  - Robinson & Royce (Box 15)
  - Robinson & music (Box 15)
  - Robinson as a traditional poet (Box 15)
  - Bibliographies: Robinson, Whitman, Puritanism & American Literature (Box 15)
  - John Dewey - Letters to a Young Man (Box 15)
  - Robert Frost - Lecture notes (Box 15)
  - Betsky: Robinson dissertation & Preston, "The Man Against the Sky" (Box 15)
  - Norman Mailer (Box 15)
  - Paul Green bibliography (Box 15)
  - English 437 - Exams (Box 15)
  - Veblen: "Pecuniary Canons of Taste" (Box 15)
  - Gertrude Stein (Box 15)
  - Lindsay, Masters, S. Anderson, W. V. Moody, Amy Lowell, E. Pound (Box 15)
  - Eugene O'Neill (Box 16)
  - Hart Crane (Box 16)
  - William Faulkner (Box 16)
  - Bellow - Seize the Day (Box 16)
  - The Peripatetic Critic (Box 16)
  - Outline for proposed Ph.D. dissertation by Davis (Box 16)
  - Notes on Humanistic Imperatives in an Age of Technology (Box 16)
  - Writings by others on India (Box 16)
  - Writings on Whitman by Indian scholars (Box 16)
  - Walt Whitman (Box 16)
  - Drafts of chapters in Robinson study (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
  - American Civilization Conference
  - Report on a Swinger of Birches by Sidney Cox (Box 16)
  - American Studies Research Centre (Box 16)
  - United States Information Agency (Box 16)
  - Six sculptors
  - Review of American Poetry: 1910-1930 (Box 16)
  - The World Exists for the Education of Each Man (Box 16)
  - History of American Poetry project (Box 16)
  - Hampton Scholarship Night
  - 1. Radio address for WYNC, 2. Speech at Hampton, 3. Article on Don Jr. (Box 16)
  - Proposed book on Critical Approaches to Literature (Box 16)
  - Correspondence with Barnard (Box 16)
  - Lucy Larcom (Box 16)
  - Whitman speech - MLA and other Whitman studies (Box 16)
  - Iowa - Afro-American Institute, Bibliography (Box 16)
  - NCTE (College Section) (Box 16)
  - Cornell - Disruption (Box 16)
  - NYU - Hatchett case (Box 16)
  - Salem witchcraft - Chad Hansen (Box 17)
  - Charlotte's book (Box 17)
  - Afro-American bibliographies & indexes (empty folder) (Box 17)
  - Applying to Medical School (Box 17)
  - Board of State Academic Awards, 1980 (Box 17)
  - Editorial project on Black Abolitionists (empty folder) (Box 17)
  - American Council of Learned Societies (Box 17)
  - American Short Story (Box 17)
  - Institute for Minority Studies (Box 17)
  - Associate Fellows: correspondence (Box 17)
  - Fiction grant proposal (Box 17)
  - Calhoun visitors, Teas & other affairs, 1975 (Box 17)
  - Calhoun seminar in Recent American Fiction (Box 17)
  - Calhoun Commencement Address, 1974 (Box 17)
  - Calhoun: Fellows correspondence (Box 17)
  - Letters on retirement from Mastership of Calhoun (Box 17)
  - Dissertation reports, 1977-1980 (Box 17)
  - Pembroke College, Oxford - Sir Geoffrey (Box 17)
  - Camps, W. Anthony. Pembroke (Cam.) (Box 17)
  - Correspondence with fellows of Calhoun (Box 17)
  - Classic Afro-American Fiction, 1827-1919 (Box 17)
  - Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences (Box 17)
  - The English Institute (Box 17)
  - Hale, Janice (Box 17)
  - Garland Publishing Company (Box 17)
  - Hall, G. K. (Box 17)
  - Italian mementos (Box 17)
  - Jackson Blyden: NEH application (Box 17)
  - Library acquisition: Wright & Cleaver (Box 17)
  - Lyttle, David (Box 17)
  - National Humanities Center meeting (Box 17)
  - Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences (Box 17)
  - Salzburg Seminar, 1973 (Box 18)
  - Salzburg Seminar: participants and addresses, 1973 (Box 18)
  - Society for the Study of Southern Literature (Box 18)
  - Spelman College: Board, 1980 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 18)
  - Spelman College (Box 18)
  - Spelman College (continued) (Box 19)
  - Yale University Press (Box 19)
  - Black Abolitionists project (Box 19)
  - Aspen Institute, 7 (Box 19)
  - Printed material (Box 19)
  - Practicing Italian (Box 19)
  - The Uses of Language (Box 19)
  - Student paper (Box 19)
  - Swarthmore (Box 19)
  - Papers by C. Davis (Box 19)
  - Printed material (Box 19)
  - Advisory Council (Box 19)
  - Printed material, correspondence (Box 19)
  - National Council of Teachers of English (Box 20)
  - Correspondence on theses: Gaugler (Box 20)
  - Commission on Literature (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 20)
  - Dartmouth - Disruption (Box 20)
  - College Language Association Conference, 1961 (Box 20)
  - Black American Artists (Box 20)
  - David Lyttle
  - American Literature Section, MLA
  - Pat LeParte (Box 20)
  - NYU - President's Council, 1969 (Box 20)
  - University Human Rights Committee (Box 20)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities (Box 20)
  - Davis, Prof. Charles T. & wife (Box 20)
  - Fulbright - Italy, 1966-1967 (Box 20)
  - "Mission" of the Teacher of American Literature, American Literature Section, MLA (Box 20)
  - Class notes - American Literature (Box 20)
  - American Civilization (Box 21)
  - Thomas Paine (Box 21)
  - Nature in 19th Century American Literature (Box 21)
  - Popular Culture in the 19th Century, 1865-1890 (Box 21)
  - Literature and Culture - 19th Century America (Box 21)
  - Literary History of the USA (Box 21)
  - American Romanticism - General (Box 21)
  - R. W. Emerson (Box 21)
  - E. A. Poe (Box 21)
  - Henry David Thoreau (Box 21)
  - Hawthorne (Box 21)
  - Calhoun - Webster - Stowe (Box 21)
  - John S. Whittier (Box 21)
  - Longfellow and Holmes (Box 21)
  - History of the USA (Box 21)
  - Herman Melville (Box 21)
  - Poetry - Notes - Lecture by H. Miller on Victorian Poetry (Box 21)
  - Hopkins, Gerard Manley (Box 21)
  - Yeats, W. B. (Box 21)
  - Angus Wilson - Facsimile of a worksheet (Box 21)
  - English 16 (Box 21)
  - English 106 (Box 21)
  - Bibliography (Box 21)
  - University of Iowa (D. Turner) (Box 21)
  - The Afro-American Experience (Box 21)
  - DuBois Institute: Introductions, discussion (Box 21)
  - Prosody (Box 21)
  - Notes - English Honors (NYU) (Box 21)
  - Reviews: Anne Bradstreet (Box 21)
  - Definitions and drama in Walden (Box 21)
  - Thoreau - Sauntering to Walden Pond (Box 21)
  - Impressionism as a Cultural Impulse (Box 21)
  - Review of American Poetry: 1910-1930 (Box 21)
  - Berkeley affair (Box 21)
  - Franklin (Box 21)
  - Speech at Virginia State College (Box 21)
  - Benston, Kimberly W.: The Shaping of the Marlovian Sublime, Dissertation, 1980 (Box 22)
  - Ford application (Box 22)
  - Honors class material (Box 22)
  - Executive Committee, Afro-American Studies (Box 22)
  - Foreword: (Davis & Blassingame) (Box 22)
  - Davis, Collis Jr. (Box 22)
  - Defining an Afro-American Tradition (Box 22)
  - The Shaping, 2 (Box 22)
  - Retention programs (Box 22)
  - Latortue, Régine (Box 22)
  - Minority students, 2 (Box 22)
  - Photocopies of poems and writings by others (Box 22)
  - Photocopies of poems and writings by others (continued) (Box 23)
  - Dennis Brutus project by Gessler M. Nkondo (Box 23)
  - W. E. B. DuBois (Box 23)
  - Richard Wright and his Influence (Box 23)
  - Richard Wright's Fiction: The Critical Response 1940-1971 (Box 24)
  - Report of the President's Commission (Penn State), 1970 (Box 24)
  - Afro-American Studies Center, 1979-1980 (Box 25)
  - Afro-American Studies - University of California (Berkeley) (Box 25)
  - American Literature Section, MLA (Box 25)
  - American Studies Association (Box 25)
  - The American Short Stories (Box 25)
  - ASA: New England Region (Box 25)
  - American Studies, Princeton: Lee C. Mitchell (Box 25)
  - American Studies Research Centre, Hyderabad (Singh) (Box 25)
  - The American University in Cairo (Box 25)
  - Amistad House, Inc., Hartford (Box 25)
  - AYA, 1980 (Box 25)
  - Association Yale Alumni (Box 25)
  - Black Abolitionist papers project (Box 25)
  - Black Middle - Upper Class, Washington D.C. - 1875-1975 (Box 25)
  - Carnegie Foundation for International Peace Internship (Box 25)
  - The Center for Independent Study, New Haven (Box 25)
  - Centre d'Etudes Afro-Americaines (Box 25)
  - Center for the Study of Southern Culture (Box 25)
  - Center for Theater Techniques in Education, Stratford, CT (Box 25)
  - Collection of Afro-American Literature, Suffolk University, Boston (Box 25)
  - Connecticut Academy of Arts & Sciences (Box 25)
  - Yale contract, Charles T. Davis (Box 25)
  - Dartmouth College (Box 25)
  - Denver Literary Group (Box 25)
  - Effort reporting: Serge Lang (Box 25)
  - Ellington Fellowships (Box 25)
  - Encyclopedia Africana (Box 25)
  - Faculty perspectives on Yale financial status (Box 25)
  - Hampton Institute (Carl Hill) (Box 25)
  - Harvard: Black Studies at Harvard (Box 25)
  - Visiting Committee, Harvard University (Box 25)
  - Joint Advisory Committee, 1975-1976 (Box 25)
  - Kirkland House - Harvard (Box 25)
  - Yale law and policy review (Box 25)
  - Masterpiece Radio Theater Education project (Box 25)
  - Minority voices (Box 25)
  - Moorland-Spingarn Research Center (Box 25)
  - NASA conference - Calhoun (Box 25)
  - National Council for Black Studies (Box 25)
  - New Black middle class prospects (Box 25)
  - Northeast Association of College & University Housing Officers, regional conference, 1980 (Box 25)
  - Notes on C's leaving the Calhoun Mastership (Box 25)
  - National Humanities faculty (Box 25)
  - Poe Studies Association (Box 25)
  - The Rockefeller Foundation: Bellagio (Box 25)
  - Sexual Harassment (grievance procedure) (Box 25)
  - South Africa - Hodding Carter (Box 25)
  - Conference on Southern Literary Study, Chapel Hill, 1972 (Box 25)
  - South African Research Program, Yale & Wesleyan (Box 25)
  - Stanford University: African and Afro-American Studies (Box 25)
  - Stanford Faculty Club (Box 25)
  - Photocopies of writings by Nathaniel Mackay (Box 25)
  - Urban League of Greater New Haven (Box 25)
  - Center of the Humanities, Wesleyan (Box 25)
  - Wesleyan: Tenure decision, William R. Ward (Esteban Vega) (Box 25)
  - Whitney Humanities Center (Box 25)
  - Wilberforce papers, University of Wisconsin-Lacrosse (Box 25)
  - Wilberforce editorial project (Box 25)
  - Yale Affirmative Action plan (Box 25)
  - Yale Alumni Fund (Box 25)
  - The History and Theory of Afro-American Literary Criticism, 1773-1831, by Henry Louis Gates, Jr., 1978 (Box 26)
  - A suggested list of subjects which an Encyclopedia of the Negro should treat; prepared by W. E. B. DuBois, 1936 (Box 26)
  - Afro-American Studies (Box 26)
  - The Shaping of the Afro-American Literary Tradition (Box 26)
  - Student dissertation (Box 26)
  - Various writings (Box 26)
  - Rosenthal, M. L. (Box 26)
  - Uncle Tom's Cabin & Josiah Henson (Box 26)
  - The Crisis, 1979 (Box 26)
  - Robin Winks (Box 26)
  - N.Y. Public Library (Schomburg Center) (Box 26)
  - Printed material, 2 (Box 26)
  - Empty envelope (Box 26)
  - Comments on Black Power (Box 27)
  - Black Coeds, Antebellum, Oberlin College (Box 27)
  - Larson: Cullen Ms. (Box 27)
  - Black fiction, Modern (Box 27)
  - Black family - Gutman (Box 27)
  - Haitian poetry & French Negro poetry (Box 27)
  - Institute on the Harlem Renaissance, 1970 (Box 27)
  - Michael S. Harper (Box 27)
  - Hayden, Robert, 2 (Box 27)
  - Himes, Chester (Box 27)
  - Hughes, Langston, papers (Box 27)
  - Iowa (Box 27)
  - Jazz: also University Without Walls (Box 27)
  - Kelley, W. (Box 27)
  - Reed, Ishmael (Box 27)
  - Milner, R. (Box 27)
  - Soyinka, Wole (Box 27)
  - Walker, Margaret & Black Women poets (Box 27)
  - Toomer, Jean, 2 (Box 27)
  - African Literature in Portuguese (Box 27)
  - Articles on Black art (Box 27)
  - Baldwin, James, 2 (Box 27)
  - Wright, Richard (Box 27)
  - Wright & Ellison, Wasseman, Skerrett (Box 27)
  - Wright, Richard (Box 27)
  - Richard Wright Archive - Description (Box 27)
  - Information on Summer Institute on R. Wright - Afro-American Studies (Box 27)
  - The Black arts and/or Black Power, speech at Harvard University, 1969 (Box 27)
  - Black Studies speech (Box 27)
  - Speech at Bryn Mawr, 1970 (Box 27)
  - Speech to Iowa Foundation & Alumni Association on Afro-American Studies Programs (Box 27)
  - Cedar Rapids - NAACP (Box 27)
  - Tribute to King (Box 27)
  - New Humanistic Frontiers in American Studies (Box 27)
  - Chapel talk: The Peaceable Kingdom, 1968 July 21 (Box 27)
  - Scribner's (Box 27)
  - Winks: The Making of a Fugitive Slave Narrative (Box 27)
  - Quarter Century Fund: Yale (Box 27)
  - On Being Black, 2 (Box 27)
  - List of texts: AA82a (Box 27)
  - MAC - PROP Sub-committee (Box 27)
  - Report of the Committee on the Status of Minority Students in the Graduate and Professional Schools (Box 27)
  - Spelman College
  - Vanity Fair, empty envelope (Box 27)
- Personal Papers, 1931-1980; Series III; 3; (5 boxes)
  Series III. Personal Papers contains additional correspondence, audiovisual material, assorted personal and militrary records, and family papers.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 38 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Hand-knitted Calhoun sweater (Box 28)
  - Tony at Yale (Box 29)
  - Curriculum vitae & S.C. Davis (Box 29)
  - Kip at Swarthmore (Box 29)
  - Davis, Anthony (Box 29)
  - Personal tributes, etc. (Box 29)
  - Kip - Drama (Box 29)
  - Davis, Charles T. (Box 29)
  - Army records (Box 29)
  - Transcripts & academic records (Box 29)
  - The Rockefeller Foundation Humanities Fellowship (Box 29)
  - Emergency telephone numbers (Box 29)
  - Mother (Box 29)
  - Davis (Box 29)
  - The Musser Chair and the Sickness, 1980 (Box 29)
  - Davis, Charles T. (Box 29)
  - Newspaper accounts of Princeton appointment, 2 (Box 30)
  - Yale Alumni Magazine and Journal, 1980 (Box 30)
  - India, 3 (Box 30)
  - Jeanne Curtis Davis resume (Box 30)
  - Empty folders (Box 30)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 30)
  - Ass[ociation] of former interns of Freedmen's Hospital, 1931 June (Box 30)
  - Correspondence, 3 (Box 30)
  - Remington (Box 30)
  - Charles Davis on American Writing, Criticism, Black Studies, Literacy, 1980 March 18; 1 (Box 38, Item barcode 39002104611786)
    Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    A typewritten letter from the National Humanities Center is included with this audiocassette. It reads: "Dear Mrs. Davis: I am sending on cassette an interview I did with Charles in March 1980, which I thought you would enjoy listening to. During one of his visits to the Center, Charles graciously agreed to discuss American literature and criticism, Afro-American studies, and other issues. Excerpts from our conversation will appear on the Center's public affairs radio program, "Soundings." I send you greetings from the staff here at the Center. If you have any questions about the tape (which is yours to keep), please let me know. Sincerely, Wayne J. Pond, Public Programs Officer
  - Photograph of Ass[ociation] of Former Interns of Freedmen's Hospital, 1931 (Box 31)
  - Song of Myself, Sec. 1-19 (1 of 2), undated; 1; 00:29:25 (Box 38, Item barcode 39002104611760)
  - Song of Myself, Sec. 20-25 and 38-52 (2 of 2), undated; 1; 00:19:22 (Box 38, Item barcode 39002104611778)
- Oversize, 0.33; (2 boxes)
  - Notes (from Series II) (Box 32)
  - Lowenthal, Rodger D. (from Series II) (Box 32)
  - Students: creative work (from Series II) (Box 32)
  - American Civilization Conference (from Series II) (Box 32)
  - Hampton Scholarship Night (from Series II) (Box 32)
  - David Lyttle (from Series II) (Box 32)
  - American Literature Section, MLA (from Series II) (Box 32)
  - Spelman College (from Series II) (Box 33)
  - Six sculptors (from Series II) (Box 33)
- Restricted Material, 2.63; (4 boxes)
  Boxes 34-37: Restricted until 2051. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Restricted papers (Box 34)
  - Restricted papers (Box 35)
  - Restricted papers (Box 36)
  - Restricted papers (Box 37)